Guide to the Metrotone Newsreels, etc. Collections MS 036
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Metrotone Newsreels, etc. Collections
1952-1979
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Hearst Metrotone News, Inc.
MS 036
125
41.75 Linear Feet 49 reels
This is a small collection of newsreels and instructional films collected by WestConn.
Provenance
The provenance is unknown for these films; however, it is likely they were originally part of the library collections at WestConn or available for use from the Audio-Visual Department.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The distribution of Hearst Metrotone newsreel was intended to bolster interest in newspapers owned by Hearst. These were the precursors to television news stories, and, though intended to be entertaining, they provide moving-image documentation of world events. The onset of the television medium ended the need for newsreels and they were gradually fazed out of theatrical distribution in the early 1960s.
However, Audio visual departments and libraries collected these materials for classroom and educational use until the mid-1980s when they were gradually replaced by videotapes and then DVDs.
Scope and Content Note
This is a small collection of Hearst Metrotone newsreels which document the Cuban revolution, the early stages of the U.S.'s space program, and other Cold War era issues. Of interest are films on Gerald Ford, Africa from 1978, and a 1966 film on the "mission to the moon."
Collected with the Metrotone Newsreels were a ca. 1960s reprint of Charlie Chaplin's "The Tramp," and 2 instructional films dealing with adolescence.
The collection was cleaned in 2003; however, some degradation is apparent.
Arrangement
Reels are arranged alphabetically by title.
Reels are grouped into 2 series.
Cold War.; Space flight to the moon; Project Apollo (U.S.); Newsreels.; Acetate film; Hearst Metrotone News, Inc.; Goddard, Robert Hutchings, 1882-1945.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970.; Castro, Fidel, 1926-; Connecticut National Bank.
- Screen News Digest Films / Hearst Metrotone News:, 39289
  - The 1964 Convention, 39331 (Film canister 1)
    General note
    (16 mm)
  - Africa Today: Changes and Challenges Volume 20, Issue 6, 1978; 39330 (Film canister 2)
    (16 mm) Accompanying discussion outline
    Stamped on cover: Presented as a public service by the Connecticut National Bank.
    Address on back of pamphlet: Screen News Digest, 235 East 45th Street, New York, NY 10017. Cloyd G. Aarseth, Producer; Martin J. Kendrick, Director.
  - The Art of Diplomacy: In the Beginning, A Special Color Report (documentary color essay) Volume 20, Issue 7, 1978; 39329 (Film canister 3)
    (16 mm) Stamped on cover: as a public service by the ConnecticutNational.
    Film is degraded.
  - Charles DeGaulle: The End of An Era, 1970; 39328 (Film canister 4)
  - Dag Hammarskjöld and the UN, 1953; 39327 (Film canister 5)
  - The DeGaulle Dilemma: A Timely Report on NATO Volume 9, Issue 2, 1966; 39326 (Film canister 6)
    Stamped on cover: as a public service by the Connecticut National Bank.
    Address on back of pamphlet: Screen News Digest, 450 West 56th Street, New York, NY 10019. C. B. Stratton, Executive Vice President, Cloyd G. Aarseth, Editor; Martin J. Kendrick, Manager.
  - Der Fuehrer: The Rise and Fall of Adolph Hitler Volume 17, Issue 8, 1975; 39325 (Film canister 7)
  - Destination Moon: A Unique Report Volume 9, Issue 6, 1967; 39324 (Film canister 8)
    Address on back of pamphlet: Screen News Digest, 450 West 56th Street, New York, NY 10019. C. B. Stratton, Executive Vice President; Cloyd G. Aarseth, Editor; Martin J. Kendrick, Manager.
  - Down on the Farm: An Agricultural Revolution Volume 12, Issue 4, 1967; 39323 (Film canister 9)
  - Dr. Robert Goddard: Father of the Space Age, 1965; 39322 (Film canister 10)
  - The Enigma of Charles DeGaulle Volume 5, Issue 9, 1962, 39321 (Film canister 11)
  - The Flight of Friendship 7: An Historic Film Report Volume 4, Issue 8, 1978; 39320 (Film canister 12)
    Address on back of pamphlet: Screen News Digest, 450 West 56th Street, New York, NY 10019. Cloyd G. Aarseth, Editor; Martin J. Kendrick, Associate Editor.
  - Focus on 1945 - Part I, 1965; 39319 (Film canister 13)
    (16 mm) Accompanying discussion outline(partial…torn in half)
  - Focus on Cuba: The Change Under Castro, 1963; 39318 (Film canister 14)
  - Focus on Cuba: The Years Under Castro Volume 8, Issue 5, 1965; 39317 (Film canister 15)
  - Focus on the United Nations: A Look at the Record Volume 6, Issue 3, 1963; 39316 (Film canister 16)
    Address on back of pamphlet: Screen News Digest, 450 West 56th Street, New York, NY 10019. Cloyd G. Aarseth, Editor; Martin J. Kendrick, Manager.
  - Focus on West Berlin: The Struggle for Survival, Volume 11, Issue 8, 1969; 39315 (Film canister 17)
    (16 mm) Accompanying discussion outline…includes announcement "We are honored to announce that the Freedoms Foundation at Valley Forge has awarded its coveted George Washington Honor Medal to The Screen News Digest as 'an outstanding accomplishment in helping to achieve a better understanding of the American Way of Life.'" This is the third time that The Screen News Digest has been so honored by the Freedoms Foundation." Stamped on cover: Presented as a public service by the Connecticut National Bank.
  - "Forward, Now, Together,"an historic color report Volume 17, Issue 1, 1974; 39314 (Film canister 18)
  - From Kitty Hawk to Jumbo Jet: A History of Aviation Volume 12, Issue 7, 1970; 39313 (Film canister 19)
    (16 mm) Accompanying pamphlet, a discussion outline: "Screen News Digest: Living History in the Classroom." Outline prepared for group leaders, teachers, and students includes a summary of the monthly feature story and background info on its main points. Stamped on cover: Presented as a public service by the Connecticut National Bank.
  - Frontiers -1965: The Sky Above, The Sea Below Volume 8, Issue 2, 39312 (Film canister 20)
    Address on back of pamphlet: Screen News Digest, 450 West 56th Street, New York, NY 10019. Cloyd G. Aarseth, Producer; Martin J. Kendrick, Manager.
  - The Lightning War In the Middle East Volume 10, Issue 1, 1967; 39311 (Film canister 21)
  - The Lone Eagle An Exclusive Film Biography Volume 19, Issue 7, 1978; 39310 (Film canister 22)
    Stamped on cover: as a public service by ConnecticutNational.
  - A Man Called "Duce:" Mussolini in Perspective Volume 14, Issue 7, 1972; 39309 (Film canister 23)
    Address on back of pamphlet: Screen News Digest, 450 West 56th Street, New York, NY 10019. Cloyd G. Aarseth, Executive Editor; Martin J. Kendrick, Executive Director.
  - The Man from Missouri: Harry S. Truman Volume 21, Issue 6, 1979; 39308 (Film canister 24)
    Stamped on cover: as a public service by the ConnecticutNational.
    Address on back of pamphlet: Screen News Digest, 450 West 56th Street, New York, NY 10019. Cloyd G. Aarseth, Producer; Martin J. Kendrick, Director.
  - Mankind and the Atom: The Challenge of Our Times Volume 21, Issue 2, 1967; 39307 (Film canister 25)
  - Mao Tse-Tung: Life and Legacy Volume 19, Issue 3, 1977; 39306 (Film canister 26)
  - Mission to the Moon: Report on Project Apollo Volume 8, Issue 6, 1966; 39305 (Film canister 27)
  - A Nation Within a Nation Volume 15, Issue 1, 1972; 39304 (Film canister 28)
    (16 mm) "An Exclusive Color Report." Accompanying discussion outline
  - Nuclear Fallout, 1963; 39303 (Film canister 29)
    (16 mm) Metrotone?
  - One Small Step Volume 14, Issue 8, 1972; 39302 (Film canister 30)
  - Portrait of a President: Lyndon Baines Johnson Volume 6, Issue 6, 1964; 39301 (Film canister 31)
  - Profile of a President: Richard Milhous Nixon Volume 12?, Issue 4, 1968; 39300 (Film canister 32)
  - Seven Days That Shook the World, 1962; 39299 (Film canister 33)
  - "Seward's Folly:" The Story of Alaska Volume 9, Issue 8, 1967; 39298 (Film canister 34)
  - Stepping Stones in Space Volume 15, Issue 5, 1973; 39297 (Film canister 35)
  - Treasures of the Nile: The MacArthur Story, 1964; 39296 (Film canister 36)
  - Troubled Neighbors: Cuba and the United States Volume 18, Issue 4, 1975; 39295 (Film canister 37)
    Slight vinegar odor
  - Turmoil in Communist China Volume 9, Issue 10, 1967; 39294 (Film canister 38)
  - The Two-Headed Dragon, 1971; 39293 (Film canister 39)
  - U.S. and China: A New Beginning Volume 21, Issue 8, 1979; 39292 (Film canister 40)
  - Vietnam Epilogue: The End of the Tunnel Volume 15, Issue 7, 1971; 39291 (Film canister 41)
    Case is rusty and dented. Needs to be replaced. Difficult to remove it.
  - A Walk on the Moon, 1969; 39290 (Film canister 42)
    (16 mm) "Special Color Release"
- Miscellaneous, 39281
  - The Tramp, Charlie Chaplin (1915), undated; 39288 (Film canister 46)
  - Washington, D.C.: Tour of Supreme Court, 1952; 39287 (Film canister 47)
    (16 mm) (cover label is illegible)
  - John F. Kennedy: The Man and President, 1963; 39286 (Film canister 48)
    (16 mm) Cover states: Thorne Films
  - Monkeys of Mysore (#6566), 1965; 39285 (Film canister 49)
    (16 mm). University of California Extension Media Center(EMC), Berkeley, CA 94720
  - Herbert Hoover and Alfred Smith: Presidential Election of, undated; 39284 (Film canister 50)
    (16 mm)(typed study guide inside case)
  - The Meaning of Adolescence McGraw-Hill Text Films, Adolescent Development Series, undated; 39283 (Film canister 51)
    (16 mm) "Intermediate Junior High, Senior High, Adult." Card inside cover states: Gasoline Age - History of Transportation, Part II, Encyclopedia Britannica Films, Inc. Reverse side of card states "This is about how children learn by doing."
  - Unidentified, undated; 39282 (Film canister 52)
    (16 mm) Damaged reel on adolescence.